Senior DevOps Engineer

Sumanth Royal

E-mail: pagadalasumanthdevops@gmail.com

Mobile: (+91)-9701441328

Objective:

Well versed in software production, development life-cycle and release of software products. Looking for a responsible position as a Build and Release Engineer in an established IT firm 5 years of experience on DevOps Engineer activities.

Profile & Achievements

- > 5 years of experience in the IT industry and implemented organization DevOps strategy in various environments of Linux servers along with adopting cloud strategies based on Google.
- Experience drawing business diagrams for google cloud platform.
- Experience in using Jenkins for continuous integration and Spinnaker for continuous deployment to deploy the microservices on to GKE.
- > Successfully led and executed the migration of on-premises or existing Google cloud infrastructure.
- Demonstrated measurable improvements in application scalability, reliability, and agility through successful Google Cloud migration projects, enabling organizations to accelerate innovation and achieve their business objectives in the cloud.
- Managing infrastructure configurations and deployments using GitLab CI/CD YAML files.
- ➤ Provisioned GKE clusters in the Google cloud environment, configuring node pools, networking, and security settings to ensure optimal performance, reliability, and compliance.
- Experience on multi-tiered infrastructure deployments and configurations using Terraform workspaces, modules, and composition techniques.
- Experience on Integrating Terraform with monitoring and logging tools such as Prometheus, Grafana.
- ➤ Knowledge and experience in implementing the entire cloud infrastructure using Terraform.
- ➤ Developing and maintain infrastructure as code (IaC) using Terraform to provision and manage cloud resources on platform on Google Cloud Platform(GCP).
- Experience in migrating the Linux/Windows on-premises VMs, physical servers using Velostrata (Migrate for Compute Engine) to Google Cloud Platform.
- ➤ Good experience in Google Cloud Stackdriver Monitoring, Logging, Error Reporting & Debugging and integrating Stackdriver with Grafana.
- ➤ Good knowledge & hands-on experience in designing the high-level architecture and low-level Architecture design for implementation of various applications on Google cloud & AWS cloud platforms.

- Experience in deploying Istio on GKE and monitoring the applications using Prometheus, Grafana and Kiali.
- Experience in creating cloud data pipelines using Cloud Pub/Sub, Google cloud storage .
- Experience in automating the development and test automation processes through CI/CD pipeline (Git, Jenkins, SonarQube, Artifactory, Docker containers).
- Experience in writing Dockerfiles and Jenkins files as per the requirements.
- Migrating on-prem workloads such as VMs as a container onto GKE.

EDUCATION QUALIFICATION:

B.com Computers from **Yogi Vemana University**

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

- Working in JCL Private Limited as Senior Devops Engineer, Bangalore from Mar 2023 Till date.
- Worked with Aeries Technology as Software Engineer, Bangalore from Aug 2022 - Feb 2023.
- Worked with Softline Private Limited as Devops Engineer, Bangalore from **Aug 2019 July 2022.**

Technical skills:

Operating Systems	Linux, UNIX & Windows	
Version Control Tools	GIT, Gitlab, Bitbucket	
Build Management Tools	Maven, ANT	
Service Mesh	Istio	
Scripting Languages	ShellScript, YAML, Terraform	
Monitoring Tools	Prometheus, Grafana	
Application Servers	Apache Tomcat, JBOSS	
Continuous Integration Tools	Jenkins, Gitlab	
Web Server	Nginx	
Configuration Tools	Ansible	
Database	Cloud SQL, Cloud BigTable, Cloud Spanner	
Virtualization Tools	Docker	
Cloud Tools	AWS, GCP	
Code Quality tools	SonarQube	
Container Management Tool	Kubernetes, Gke	
Ticketing Tools	Atlassian Jira, Slack	

ICL Private Limited.

Project: OCI Migration Project Duration: Mar 2023 - Till date

Designation: Senior Devops Engineer.

Tools: Google Cloud Platform(GCP), Terraform, Jenkins, Git, Gitlab, OneArtifactory, Ant, minikube, kubernetes, K9s, Docker, Helm, Maven, CI/CD, Shell scripting, GKE, Newrelic, CloudSQL, catchpoint, SonarQube, Fortify scan, Logstash, Jira, Ansible.

Roles & Responsibilities:

- Creating and modifying Terraform configuration files (.tf) to define infrastructure resources such as virtual machines, networks, storage, and services.
 - Applying Terraform configurations to provision and manage infrastructure resources across multiple cloud providers or on-premises environments.
- Version control Terraform configurations using Git or other version control systems to track changes and collaborate with team members.
- Review and merge pull requests for Terraform code changes to maintain code quality.
- > Orchestrate complex multi-tiered infrastructure deployments and configurations using Terraform workspaces, modules, and composition techniques.
- Integrate Terraform with monitoring and logging tools such as Prometheus, Grafana.
- Manage multiple environments such as development, staging, production using Terraform workspaces or separate configuration files to maintain isolation and consistency across environments.
 - Applying Terraform configurations to provision and manage infrastructure resources for new projects or applications, ensuring alignment with project requirements and architectural standards.
- Software Configuration management (Build and continuous Integration using Maven, Jenkins & GIT, Gitlab.)
- Created release branches in GIT by GIT Administration including branching.
- > Creating CI/CD pipelines by integrating Git, Gitlab, Maven, Jenkins, Ansible.
- ➤ Installed Jenkins on a Linux machine and created a master and slave configuration to implement multiple parallel builds through a build farm.
- ➤ Integrated monitoring and logging solutions, such as Prometheus, and Grafana, to monitor GKE cluster health, performance, and resource utilization, ensuring proactive management and troubleshooting.
- Responsible for creating Builds and Deployments Planes.
- Creating War/Jar files using Maven.
- ➤ Hands on experience in installing and administrating CI tools like Jenkins and GIT. Gitlab.
- Leveraged GitLab's IaC capabilities, such as GitLab CI/CD YAML configurations, to automate infrastructure provisioning and configuration management tasks.
- executed the migration of on-premises or existing cloud-based workloads to Google Kubernetes Services(GKE).
- Good experience in implementing the entire cloud infrastructure using Terraform.

- Configure alerting and logging for Terraform operations to track changes, diagnose problems, and troubleshoot issues quickly.
- Implement security best practices and compliance standards in Terraform configurations to ensure the security and compliance of infrastructure resources.
- Scan Terraform configurations for security vulnerabilities and compliance violations using static analysis tools and automated checks.
- ➤ Configure alerting and logging for Terraform operations to track changes, diagnose problems, and troubleshoot issues quickly.
- ➤ Integrating Terraform with monitoring and logging tools such as Prometheus, Grafana.
- ➤ Building/Maintaining Docker container clusters managed by Kubernetes, GIT, Docker, on Google cloud Platform(GCP). Utilized Kubernetes, K9s and Docker for the runtime environment of the CI / CD system to build, test and deploy.
- ➤ Using Kubernetes, K9s to orchestrate the deployment, scaling and management of Docker Containers.
- Responsible for taking the source code and compiling using Maven and package it in its distributable format, such as a Jar/War.
- Perform Build activities using Maven, Jenkins and Gitlab tools.
- Perform Deployment of War files in Tomcat application servers using Shell scripts.
- Written Ansible playbooks to automate installation of Middleware Infrastructure like Apache Tomcat, JDK and configuration tasks for new environments etc
- ➤ Perform smoke/sanity tests for the applications deployed and also troubleshoot the application for the issues that arise as part of the smoke test process.
- Wrote Shell scripts for doing Deployment and take the Git repository backups.
- Experience working on Docker hub, creating Docker images and handling multiple images primarily for middleware installations and domain configurations.
- Design and create automated Build and Deployment process.
- ➤ Newrelic Implementation for Application performance Monitoring Catch point for Performance Monitoring Fortify for Code scan SonarQube Integration for code Quality check.
- Creating pipelines for Automating sonarQube and Fortify.

ATG Business Solutions Private Limited (Aeries).

Project: Migration project on GCP - Tesla

Duration: Aug 2022 - Feb 2023 Designation: Software Engineer

Tools: Google Cloud Platform(GCP), Docker, Minikube, Kubernetes, K9s, Terraform, Tomcat, Jenkins, Maven, Tomee, Jenkins, Jira, Slack, Git, Ci/Cd, Github, Gitlab, Istio, Helm, Podman, GKE, ArgoCD etc.

Roles & Responsibilities:

- Building and Maintain Docker container clusters managed by Kubernetes, Gitlab, Docker, on Google Cloud Platform (GCP).
 Utilized Kubernetes,K9s and Docker for the runtime environment of the CI/CD system to build, test and deploy.
- Deploying in Minikube and Kubernetes.
- Deploying in QA,PPD and PROD.
- > Raising the PR for review.
- Committing code changes to GitLab repositories.
- Writing build Maven and pom.xml for the projects.
- ➤ Maintaining Docker containers using Minikube.
- ➤ Good Experience in working with Google Kubernetes Engine(GKE) deployment and HPA.
- Configuration Management and Automation tools.
- Software development methodologies.
- ➤ Version control Terraform configurations using Git or other version control systems to track changes and collaborate with team members.
- ➤ Developed and maintained infrastructure as code (IaC) using Terraform to provision and manage cloud resources on platform on Google Cloud Platform(GCP).
- Review and merge pull requests for Terraform code changes to maintain code quality.
- ➤ Integrated Terraform with continuous integration/continuous deployment CI/CD pipelines such as GitLab CI/CD to automate the deployment of infrastructure changes as part of the software delivery process.
- ➤ Implemented Terraform-driven CI/CD pipelines to promote infrastructure changes across multiple environments.
- Creative problem solving and analysis skills with an ability to identify develop and implement solutions to gaps to meet the needs of the business.
- ➤ Delivered high service levels by maintaining a 95% service level agreement rate during peak times.
- ➤ Implementing backup and disaster recovery strategies for GitLab repositories and CI/CD pipelines.
- ➤ Implemented and maintained CI/CD pipelines with GitLab CI/CD to automate the build, test, and deployment processes, resulting in faster release cycles and improved software quality.
- ➤ Monitoring CI/CD pipelines for automated builds, tests, and deployments triggered by code changes.
 - Troubleshooting pipeline failures and addressing issues promptly.
- Managing infrastructure configurations and deployments using GitLab CI/CD YAML files.
- ➤ Making changes to infrastructure code and reviewing merge requests related to infrastructure changes.

- ➤ Taking up code reviews and collaborated with team members using GitLab merge requests MRs, providing feedback and ensuring code quality and standards adherence.
- > Build automation for common operational tasks.
- Strong ability to interact with all levels of the organization.
- > Cloning the latest repo's where latest commits done.
- ➤ Actively contribute to process improvement across the organization.
- ➤ Identifying the data migration impact of all proposed changes.
- Owning the quality of the migrated data and the validity of the migration processes and operation.
- ➤ Integration software system implementation with cae management.
- Strong understanding in Integration Migration Activities.

Softline Solutions Private Limited.

Project: Banking Project on GCP Duration: Aug 2019-July 2022 Designation: Devops Engineer

Tools: GCP, AWS, Jenkins, Maven, Terraform, Git, Kubernetes, Auto Scaling, Ci/Cd, Docker, Istio, Spinnaker, Shell scripting, Helm, Grafana, Jira, GKE, Cloud SQL ect.

Roles & Responsibilities:

- Actively involved in the design of high-level and low-level architecture design of On-premises development, test, staging, and production environment to Google cloud platform.
- Creating the required firewall rules and routes with proper network tags for secured communication using VPC.
- ➤ Deploying Jenkins and Spinnaker using Helm on to GKE private cluster for continuous integration and continuous deployment of different microservices and web apps.
- ➤ Good Experience in working with Google Kubernetes Engine deployment and HPA
- Experience in implementing the entire cloud infrastructure using Terraform.
- Version control Terraform configurations using Git or other version control systems to track changes.
- modify Terraform configuration files to define infrastructure resources such as virtual machines, networks, storage, and services.
- infrastructure deployments and configurations using Terraform workspaces, modules, and composition techniques.
- Experience with Kubernetes, K9s to orchestrate the deployment, scaling and management of Docker Containers.
- > containerization of applications using Docker, defining Kubernetes deployment manifests and Helm charts for seamless deployment and management on GKE clusters.

- ➤ Maintaing Docker container clusters managed by Kubernetes, GIT, Docker, on GCP and AWS.
- ➤ Trigger manual builds when necessary, such as for hotfixes or urgent patches. Ensure that Jenkins is configured to automatically trigger builds in response to code commits or other events, such as pull requests or merge requests.
- ➤ Monitor Jenkins pipelines for any ongoing builds or deployments.
- Managing infrastructure configurations and deployments using Jenkins CI/CD YAML files.
 - Check the status of pipelines to ensure that builds are running smoothly and deployments are successful.
- ➤ Setup Monitoring using Istio on GKE and Stack driver on GCP console.
- Created various dashboards for monitoring in Grafana and Stack driver as per the requirement.
- > Setup different alerting on the various resources based on thresholds in Stack driver and Grafana.
- ➤ Migration of On-prem VMs from VMware Vcenter to Google cloud platform using Velostrata (Migrate for Compute Engine).
- Utilized Kubernetes, and Docker for the runtime environment of the CI/CD system to build, test and deploy.
- > Setup of locust load testing for web-facing applications.
- Following Atlassian Jira and working according to the Sprint.
- Organizing daily standup calls with the internal team and weekly meetings with clients for syncup & report submission.

Declaration:

I hereby declare that the above stated information is true and correct to the best of my
knowledge

Date:	(Sumanth)
-------	-----------